THOUGHTS ON APL
BY BRETT SCHRANK AND TIMOTHY DOWNEY


The APL programming language has a curious reputation amongst computer 
scientists.  On the one hand, those who choose to investigate its 
workings find that its array processing capabilities and strong emphasis on
mathematical problem solving encourages creative solutions for common tasks.  
That is, many traditional approaches to programming involve looping or other 
forms of flow control to accomplish complicated functions, which work well 
but may become tedious or complicated for the coder.  Most popular languages,
like C, Java, or Fortran, utilize this method, offering few outlets for 
entirely unique routes in problem solving.  APL, on the other hand, relies 
much more upon the large-scale application of its primitives, completing 
tasks over entire arrays at once and reducing the need for much explicit 
looping.  While some programmers find this approach fascinating, others are
less than captivated by the symbolic nature and esoteric application of 
the language.  Readability and writability, unlike most other high-level 
languages, become major hindrances to usage of APL, and most people seem to
be under the impression that they cannot be bothered to learn and understand
something so complicated.  Thus began our exploration into the APL language,
as we attempted to discover for ourselves whether APL is truly worth the 
time invested to master it.  This investigation, more importantly, was 
done through the eyes of fairly new programmers, giving a new perspective
on what it is like to learn APL for someone not--put rather bluntly--
"tainted" by other programming languages.

Our journey focused on reading through the primary tutorial on Dyalog APL,
"Mastering Dyalog APL:  A Complete Introduction to Dyalog APL" by Bernard
Legrand.  As we progressed through the book, we recorded our experiences--
detailing everything from what we found interesting to what came across
as particularly challenging--within journal logs.  These various entries 
constituted a source of raw, introspective data, and it is the purpose 
of this section to summarize and interpret the large quantity of personal 
thought contained within them.  In addition to reading the "Mastering Dyalog"
text, we also applied our newfound knowledge of APL firsthand through the
development of the NAS Parallel Benchmarks and the completion of Project Euler 
problems.  This enabled us to form our opinions on multiple levels: both as
students and developers.

There is a great deal to find intriguing about APL, and what first caught our 
attention was, fundamentally, the many unique features that the language has to
offer.  APL is an array processing language, meaning that the majority of
its operations are allotted to the storing, traversing, and morphing of data 
within lists and arrays.  Naturally, an array processing language should offer 
a variety of functions to make manipulating data as simple and natural as 
possible.  APL does not disappoint in this regard--one can easily add, 
subtract, concatenate, index, remove items, and create arrays with extremely
little effort on the programmer's end.  This benefit was visible within the 
first hour of practicing the language, as captured in the very first journal
entry:

"I could not help but be impressed by what I saw in my introductory glimpse 
into APL.  Just ask the friend sitting next to me as I pored over the first
several pages of the Dyalog APL tutorial book--he was the unfortunate soul
who had to endure me incessantly bringing my laptop over to him, showing him
a cool maneuver with an APL array, and returning to my work again, only to
repeat the process five minutes later...what really stuck out to me was the 
language's ability to handle arrays and related structures with such ease,
providing the coder with great flexibility in arranging and working with their
data."

It's important to note that these incredibly useful aspects are not just 
limited to simple arrays.  Multidimensional data structures also support this 
flexibility and even include their own host of features.  These range from 
transposition to matrix inverses to outer and inner products of data, along 
with many others that would surely appeal to the programmer's inner 
mathematician.  What is typically a monotonous, yet necessary, task in more 
traditional languages becomes refreshing, quick, and noticeably easier in APL.
Since less time and space is spent on "filler code" for data manipulation, APL 
functions consequently become much more compact and lightweight.

This leads to the next point of interest for APL:  the amount of room devoted
to actual code in APL appears almost microscopic in comparison to other 
languages.  Because so much activity occurs within APL's primitives,
and because we can align one-by-one a multitude of these single-character 
functions on a single line, the typical user-defined operation in APL is 
highly compressed in size and--in many cases--completely viewable as a whole
piece.  What is minimal in terms of coding space is also minimal in terms of
time taken to write.  Generally, APL functions may be developed at a rapid 
pace and modified just as rapidly if necessary.  In fact, this is one of the 
key reasons why APL is preferred over other languages in certain industries.
According to the "Mastering Dyalog APL" text, APL is incredibly versatile in
the financial and actuarial sectors where code must be developed and iterated 
on a moment's notice.  To examine this aspect of APL in practice, one need only
observe the benchmarks provided in the preceding pages.  Whereas the reference
implementation of these programs provided by NASA involved hundreds of lines
of C or Fortran code, all of these benchmarks so far have demanded 
approximately a hundred lines or less of APL code to run.  It comes as 
somewhat of a paradox that what is meant to improve readability of code can 
also serve as a hindrance to completely understanding it.  That is to say, 
while short APL programs allow the programmer to observe the entirety of their 
work at once without having it broken up into various segments, the inclusion 
of too many details on a single line can significantly stymie the transparency 
of the line.  One must be wary not to become so entranced by APL's short-code 
phenomenon that they forget to break up their lines lest they obfuscate their
code to the extent that it is nearly impossible for an outsider to understand.

As mentioned previously, APL's diminished focus on looping and other 
traditional flow control constructs allows new and unique solutions to
problems to emerge.  For those who are familiar with mathematical syntax and
concepts, APL becomes very comfortable and easy to work with, and even for one
who is not mathematically trained, it is relatively intuitive to write 
programs in APL.  For many user-defined functions, solving the task at hand
essentially reduces down to finding the right combination of primitives to 
modify data.  Rather than wasting time figuring out how to properly loop 
through data or mastering the syntax of a more traditional language, one ends
up determining how to creatively approach the problem and subsequently 
encoding it exactly as they might mentally envision it.  APL tends to 
exhibit phenomenal translational qualities for algorithms--a prime example of
this occurs in the EP benchmark from earlier, where the entirety of the 
program follows almost directly from the procedure outlined in the NPB 
documentation.  That is, once we see the math behind a problem, we can easily
convert it over to workable code.  The idea behind this is captured well
within another excerpt of our journal entries:

"I have come to a greater appreciation of the wide scope of solutions one can
conjecture for problems in APL...this encourages creativity and flexibility
when coding, and it is fun to come up with unique ways to solve problems...
APL seems to encourage cleverness rather than rote technique in such 
solutions, and idea which occurred to me after glancing at some of the 
solutions [to various problems in the book] and thinking I would never have
imagined implementing such a unique method.  The simplicity of APL goes 
hand-in-hand with this, as I am still astonished at how more involved problems
can be encapsulated within a single line or two of code."

Perhaps the greatest aspect of APL's unique solution approach is that APL is
fairly easy to write.  While this may seem completely surprising at first, due
to the number of symbols and primitives, the idea is that if you can 
intuitively conjure up a solution to a problem, then APL likely has the
tool that you need at your fingertips--all you must do is begin typing.  It is 
rather surprising to visualize how quickly and naturally APL code comes to the
programmer; once he or she begins writing, the very least of their concerns 
involve memorizing the hotkeys for the symbols.  As such, programming in APL
is a wholly different experience than writing code in other more traditional 
languages.  Often times, this means that solving problems in APL becomes 
interesting and, dare we say, fun.  Of course, the main drawback to this aspect
of APL is that one can easily become consumed with always attempting to find 
the most "APL-like solution."  This can become tiring and time-consuming after 
some time.  A brief slice of our journal entries touches upon this compulsion:

"I remember reading something online related to this while I was researching
APL in general--a common joke about APL is that if you could not solve the 
problem with just a single line of code, then you were approaching it wrong."

The APLer's dilemma, then, is to perpetually seek out these concise statements
that tersely, yet beautifully, fulfill the problem at hand.  Such pursuits,
unfortunately, are not always practical.

As one may begin to see through this discussion, APL is not without its share 
of drawbacks.  Perhaps the greatest challenge in using the language is what
immediately scares most people away without even a second glance.  APL's code 
is rather difficult to read.  This problem rears itself in two major ways.  
First, since APL is grounded so heavily in numbers and symbols, one who is 
at all unversed in the meaning of the symbols is out of luck in determining 
what the program is doing.  Even one who has studied the language in depth may 
have trouble recalling what a specific primitive does or how its meaning can
change depending on the context (such as monadically or dyadically) it is used
in.  In addition to this, because APL uses so many symbols, there are very few 
words to rely on for intuitively discerning what the programmer intended in a 
specific section.  In other programming languages, even if one has no clue what 
the program is doing, one can still perhaps formulate clues as to the program's
nature based on the high-level presentation of the code.  The NPB reference
implementations provided a good foil for us to compare to APL.  Although we had
never worked with C and Fortran code before, we were able to establish a basic 
understanding of their procedures.  If we had been presented with reference
implementations coded in APL, we fear that this would have been impossible.

Additionally, APL code can be very difficult to read due to how crowded its 
lines can become.  Just as compact coding in APL is a gift in terms of saving 
time and space, it can also be a curse when trying to unpack each line and 
determine how it fits in with the entire program.  So many operations can 
occur on one line that it becomes challenging to keep track of what has 
been computed or what has yet to be computed; combine this with APL's 
somewhat confusing right-to-left order of operations, and the task can become
downright unruly.  It is often said that APL is a "write-only" language, 
meaning that writing code in APL is much easier than reading it.  After 
spending time writing in APL and experiencing difficulty in reading our own 
code, we have determined that this statement is, for us at least, fairly 
accurate.

Another disadvantage to using Dyalog APL is having to deal with certain 
unfortunate aspects of the language itself.  One of the largest complications 
we have experienced while writing the NAS Parallel Benchmarks in APL has been 
drastic speed reductions in comparison to the reference (C and Fortran) 
implementation.  As of this moment, we suspect that the main culprit
behind these slowdowns is that Dyalog APL is an interpreted rather than 
compiled language.  In addition to this, APL utilizes what are known as
idioms, which are specific phrases of code that are recognized specially by
the interpreter.  Upon encountering an idiom, the interpreter is able to 
greater parallelize the process at hand and achieve much better performance 
than writing the same task in a different manner.  Therefore, in order to 
best optimize a certain section of code, one should attempt to include these
idioms wherever possible.  However, if these idioms are unknown to the 
programmer, or if they are unable to implement a certain idiom in a given 
location, then their code has the potential to run particularly slow. 
Another concern regarding the APL language itself is the structure of system 
variables and the dependence of primitives upon these variables.  In other 
words, if one were to alter the system variables in place, then some primitive
functions would change in their behavior.  The reason this is done is to 
maintain compatibility with legacy APL systems (such as the original IBM 
implementation). One journal entry in particular described how this could
potentially hinder code readability:

"I'm not too keen on the ⎕ML system function.  I understand that it's 
necessary to maintain compatibility with other flavors of APL, but I feel that
it is yet another obfuscating layer that makes the language more difficult to
comprehend...it could be very confusing to work with since changing the ?ML
value changes the operation of the function."

Although the preceding is a rather specific point of the language, it 
highlights an underlying difficulty to using APL--namely, it can be simply
confusing to use.  Part of this difficulty arises from the fact that learning
APL is unlike learning more traditional languages.  Although the "Mastering 
Dyalog APL" tutorial does well in highlighting the interest details of 
APL, it fails to capture what we perceive as the "trial-and-error" nature of 
the language.  That is, the best way to memorize and learn how to utilize the 
primitives and syntax of APL is to simply try it out and witness it firsthand.  
Unfortunately, this is something that is nearly impossible to convey in a
static text such as "Mastering Dyalog."  The following journal excerpt 
elaborates on this concept in greater detail:

"Although I have a surface-level understanding of what they are used for and 
how they are used, I personally find the examples in the text to be a bit dry
and hard to absorb.  I think if APL were to be taught in a general 
undergraduate level computer science course then there needs to be some 
alternative method of teaching these sections.  I think maybe even a video-
lecture style format (like the Khan Academy) might be more valuable... 

For me, at least, watching Aaron try things out and viewing actual examples of the 
coding process was infinitely more helpful than just reading the examples in the 
book."

APL itself already has a very high learning curve, which can be rather
discouraging for any hopefuls eager to learn the language, but the fact that
the language is presented in, what we believe, a rather unintuitive manner can 
be even more daunting.  Add this to the fact that researching APL online can be
difficult due to the limited size of the userbase and unusual Unicode character 
set, and trying to learn the language as a beginner becomes quite a sizeable 
feat.  If these limitations are to be overcome, we believe it is critical for 
some sort of support network to exist.  Unfortunately, this presents a sort of
catch-22.  

Although such an ideal APL coding community cannot arise overnight, other
resources can be developed, however.  Online resources such as the 
"Conway's Game of Life" video and REPL's such as TryAPL.org are an excellent 
beginning, but we believe that there is still much that can be done on this 
front.  Whether it be through interactive online tutorials or through other
methods that have yet to be imagined, we think that better learning methods
have to exist.  After all, it follows that a nontraditional language should be
taught in nontraditional ways.

Through the exploration completed in this discussion thus far, we have shown 
that APL possesses a number of fantastic characteristics and negative aspects.
The question remains:  which one wins?  Do the benefits of APL outweigh the
downsides, thus deeming it as a language truly worthwhile to learn and use?
It is clear that APL possesses a high learning curve to even begin using in 
simple applications, and even once one does become familiar with the language,
it still suffers problems such as challenging readability and structural 
drawbacks.  However, the positive features of APL, including flexible and 
powerful array processing, compact coding, and interesting methods for solving
problems, are fairly unique to the language, and experiencing these benefits 
is certainly worth the time invested in learning it--even as a purely
intellectual pursuit.  Although APL is no longer widely used, it still remains 
a perfectly valid option for a great deal of practical applications and its
inherent parallelizability hints at a possible APL renaissance in the near
future as multiprocessor systems become more and more prevalent. Simply refer 
to the NAS Parallel Benchmarks above for one small example where APL as a 
language shines in all its glory.